Guide to the Astuto, Phillip L. (collector) - Manuscripts by Francisco Xavier Eugenio de Santa Cruz y Espejo
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Astuto, Phillip L. (collector) - Manuscripts by Francisco Xavier Eugenio de Santa Cruz y Espejo
1779-1981.
Astuto, Philip L., collector.
1.5 linear ft. (11 reels, 1 volume, & 1 typescript in boxes).
Columbia University Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Butler Library, New York, NY 10027.
4079760
History
Philip Louis Astuto, 1923-, (Columbia University M.A., 1947; Ph.D., 1956) is a professor of Spanish at St. John's University.
Scope and Content
Microfilm copies of manuscripts by Francisco Xavier Eugenio de Santa Cruz y Espejo (1747-1795), early Ecuadorian political figure and precursor of Ecuadorian independence. Espejo, a doctor, helped found the Escuela de Concordia in Quito. Prof. Astuto copied these manuscripts from various governmental and private libraries in Ecuador and Colombia while on a research fellowship from the Organization of American States in 1973 and on a research grant from St. John's University in 1975. The collection includes a printed volume of three of Espejo's works edited by Astuto in 1981 & his typescript (1,184 p., with his corrections) of Las Obras Educativas by Espejo.
Subjects
Organization of American States.; St. John's University (New York, N.Y.); Santa Cruz y Espejo, Francisco Xavier Eugenio de, 1747-1795.; Colombia--History--To 1810.; Ecuador--History--To 1809.; Ecuador--Politics and government--To 1809.; Quito (Ecuador)--History.; Manuscripts for publication.; Microfilms.; College teachers.; Historians.; Physicians.; Statesmen.
Access Restrictions
Collection is shelved off-site and requires advance notice of intent to use.
Acquisition
02/13/92 M-92-02-13 Microfilms & printed book Astuto, Philip L. Gift
09/24/92 M-92-09-24 Typescript Astuto, P.L. Gift
Gift of Prof. Philip L. Astuto, 1992.
- Microfilms
  - Manuscript Works of Francisco Javier Eugenio de Santa Cruz y Espejo (1747-1795) found in various governmental and private libraries in Ecuador and Colombia between 1973 and 1975. (Box 1)
  - I. Las Obras Educativas
    - A. _E1_ Nuevo Luciano de_ Quito o Despertador de los ingenios quiteños en nueve conversaciones eruditas para el estimulo de la literatura.
      - 1. Ms. in private library: Biblioteca del Sr. D. Carlos Manuel Larrea, Quito, Ecuador. (Box 1)
      - 2. Ms. in private library: Biblioteca "Aurelio Espinosa Pólit," Library of the Society of Jesus, Cotocallao, Ecuador. (Box 1)
    - B. Marco Porcio Catón o Memorias para la impugnación del Nuevo Luciano de Quito.
      - 1. Ms. in governmental archive: Biblioteca Nacional de Bogotá, Sección de Raros y Curiosos, Ms. 279, Bogota, Colombia. (Box 1)
    - C. El Nuevo Luciano de Quito o Despertador de los ingenios quiteños en siete diálogos apologéticos de la Oración Fúnebre que dijo el Dr. Dn. Ramón de Yepez, abogado de los Reales Consejos, Cura y Vicario de la Doctrina de Tumbaco, y de las Nueve Conversaciones que salieron por Junio de 1779. [Popularly known as La Ciencia Blancardina]
      - 1. Ms. in private library: Biblioteca de Jacinto Jijón y Caamaño, Quito, Ecuador. (Box 1)
      - 2. Ms. in private library: Biblioteca del Sr. Dr. D. Miguel Diaz Cueva, Cuenca, Ecuador. (Box 1)
  - II. Obra cientifica y médica de Espejo
    - A. Reflexiones... acerca... de las viruelas.
      - 1. Ms. in private library: Biblioteca de Jacinto Jijón y Caamaño, Quito, Ecuador. N, B. Reflexiones is bound together with La Ciencia Blancardina. (Box 1)
      - 2. Ms. in private archive: Archivo del Instituto Nacional Mejía, Quito, Ecuador. (Box 1)
      - 3. Espejo ms. published in part, see Francisco Gil, Disertación fisico-médica... 2nd ed. (Madrid, 1986). (Box 1)
  - III. Obras sobre economia politica
    - A. Representación de los curas... de_ Riobamba
      - 1. Ms. in private library: Biblioteca de Jacinto Jijón y Caamaño, Quito, Ecuador. (Box 1)
      - 2. Ms. in governmental archive: Archivo Nacional de Historia, Núcleo del Azuay, Cuenca, Ecuador.
        - a. Representación ..is part of a collection of documents entitled: Espejo: Documentos y escritos de Alberto Múñoz Vernaza (Box 1)
    - B. Las Primicias de la Cultura de Quito (7 issues published)
      - 1. Ms. in private library: Biblioteca de Jacinto Jijón y Caamaño, Quito, Ecuador. (Edición facsímile) (Box 1)
  - IV. Las Obras Religiosas
    - A. Cartas teológicas escritas por el Doctor Don Francisco Javier Eugenio Santa Cruz y Espejo, natural de Quito. (N. B. This ms. codex contains two theological letters -- Cartas teologicas -- and five sermons -- Cinco sermons -- in one binder; N. B. Ms. in private library: Biblioteca de Jacinto Jijón y Caamaño, Quito, Ecuador.
      - 1. Cartas teológicas
        - a. Primera carta a Don Pasucal Cárdenas, en respuesta a una consulta, que éste hizo al Rmo. P. Francisco de la Graña, sobre asunto de indulgencias. (1780) (Box 1)
        - b. Segunda carta teológica sobre la Inmaculada Concepción de Maria. (1792) (Box 1)
      - 2. Sermones varios escritos por el Doctor Espejo.
        - a. Sermón de Dolores. (1779) (Box 1)
        - b. Sermon de San Pedro. (1780) (Box 1)
        - c. Sermon moral. (1780) (Box 1)
        - d. Primer sermon panegírico de Santa Rosa. (1793) (Box 1)
        - e. Segundo panegírico de Santa Rosa. (1794) (Box 1)
  - Printed volume: Obra Educativa. Edicion, prologo, notas y cronologia/Philip L. Astuto. [Caracas] Biblioteca Ayachucho [1981] 551 p. (Box 1)
- Manuscripts
  - Obras Educativas. Typescript: pp. 1-715 (Box 2)
  - Obras Educativas. Typescript: pp. 716 - 1,184 (Box 3)